Register of the Vladimir Milanović Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vladimir Milanović Papers
1868-1972
70078
Milanović, Vladimir J.
12 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (5.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains writings, diaries, correspondence, notes, bulletins, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Yugoslav foreign relations, especially during World War II, postwar conditions in Yugoslavia, and Yugoslav émigré affairs. Includes memoirs entitled "Iz nedavne prošlosti" relating to Yugoslav relations with Germany and Bulgaria, 1939-1941, prior to the German invasion of Yugoslavia and draft notes for an English-Serbian dictionary. Also available on microfilm (18 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1970.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate form available
Also available on microfilm (18 reels).
Biographical Note
1896 Born, Smederevo, Serbia
1906-1914 Educated in Smederevo and Belgrade, Serbia
1919 Received a diploma, specialized in diplomacy from the Ecole Libre des Science Politiques
1922 Passed doctoral exams at the Faculté de Droit, Université de Paris, France
1924 Royal Yugoslav second secretary at the embassy in
1935 Royal Yugoslav ambassador in Sofia, Bulgaria
1939-1940 Royal Yugoslav chargé d'affaires to Switzerland
1940-1941 Royal Yugoslav ambassador in Sofia, Bulgaria
1941-1944 Royal Yugoslav government-in-exile secretary general of the Foreign Ministry, London, United Kingdom
1944 Royal Yugoslav government-in-exile delegate to the Allied Commission
1944-1945 Royal Yugoslav government-in-exile ambassador to Belgium and Luxemburg
1945-1972 Settled in London; active member of the Yugoslav émigré community
1972 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers relate to the foreign relations of Royal Yugoslavia, especially during World War II, Bulgarian internal and foreign affairs, the Macedonian issue, German aspirations in the Balkan region, postwar conditions in Yugoslavia, and Yugoslav émigré affairs. They include memoirs entitled "Iz nedavne prošlosti," describing Yugoslav relations with Germany and Bulgaria from 1939 to 1941, prior to the German invasion of Yugoslavia, and draft notes for an English-Serbian dictionary.
Milanović's handwritten Diaries in Serbo-Croatian provide a private perspective on his daily routine and social life from 1938 to 1968. A Biographical file provides information on Milanović's family background, personal life, and career. Documents record the family inheritance from Smederevo and the death of Milanović's brother, Alekandar. The Correspondence includes exchanges with his close personal friends, Yugoslav émigré members, family members, particularly his nephew Milorad M. Drachkovitch (Drašković), and members of the Serbian Orthodox community in the United Kingdom.
The Speeches and writings are comprised of draft fragments, books, articles, booklets, open letters, and notes on topics related to his memoir and a considerable number of handwritten notes on English and Serbian words in preparation for a draft of an English-Serbian dictionary. Speeches and writings by others contain Milorad M. Drachkovitch's writings addressing issues related to the political system in post-war Yugoslavia and writings by others reflecting on the events in Yugoslavia during World War II, as well as developments in post-war Yugoslavia.
The Royal Yugoslav government office file consists of records Milanović collected during his diplomatic career with the Royal Yugoslav government, organised by posting. Embassy reports provide detailed information on the Royal Yugoslav government's diplomatic affairs in Bulgaria and Germany, and especially address Bulgarian politics, the Macedonian issue, and German aspirations in the Balkan region prior to World War II. Additional records document the émigrés who served the Royal Yugoslav government in London during World War II and were not able to return to Yugoslavia for political reasons.
The Photographs depict Milanović's official engagements and events during his diplomatic career, his private social life, as well as family members and personal friends. The Oversize materials contain documents on Milanović's inheritance from Smederevo in Serbia, degrees, and employment certificates. Also included are materials from the Royal Yugoslav government embassy in Bulgaria transferring the office to the new ambassador, and inventory lists of the embassy offices in Sofia and Varna, Bulgaria.
The Printed Matter consists of newspapers, journals, press releases, clippings and other materials providing daily news of developments in Yugoslavia and Europe during World War II, and the views and reflections on political and economic conditions in post-war Yugoslavia.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into nine series: Diaries, Biographical file, Correspondence, Speeches and writings, Speeches and writings by others, Royal Yugoslav government-in-exile office file, Photographs, Printed matter and Oversized materials
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
World War, 1939-1945--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; Bulgaria--Foreign relations--Yugoslavia.; Germany--Foreign relations--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--Bulgaria.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--Germany.; Yugoslavia--Emigration and immigration.; Yugoslavia--History.; Diplomats--Yugoslavia.
Collection Contents
- Diaries, 1938-1968 (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically
  - 1938-1960 (Folder 1: 1)
  - 1961-1968 (Folder 1: 2)
- Biographical file, 1868-1971 (Box 1-2)
  Includes certificates, travel documents, memorabilia, and maps of Royal Yugoslavia and the Balkans.
  Arranged by physical form
  - Personal documents, 1868-1971 (Folder 1)
    - Inheritance, Smederevo, 1868-1970 (Folder 1: 3)
      See also oversize material
    - Military certificates, 1917; 1923 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Employment records, 1917; 1924,; 1930,; 1939 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Savings book and household budget, 1934-1943; 1941-1956,; 1972,; 1973 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Birth certificates issued in, 1936 and 1961 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Party invitations letter, 1937 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Aleksandar Milanović, 1938 (Folder 1: 9)
      Includes death certificate
    - Travel documents, 1941; 1952,; 1964 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Membership cards and hotel bills, 1944; 1957,; 1968-1969 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Medical appointment records, 1967-1971 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Rent and pension records, 1966-1971 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Obituary in Srpska Borba, 7 July 1972 (Folder 1: 14)
    - Business cards and address clippings, undated (Folder 1: 15)
    - Christmas cards, postcards and a picture music disk, undated (Folder 1: 16)
  - Miscellany, undated (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes notes, a card with religious motif, a printed portrait of Draža Mihailović, and exhibition and conference programs and leaflets
  - Maps, undated (Folder 2: 2)
    - Bartholomew's Map of Italy and the Balkans, printed and published by John Bartholomew & Son, ltd., Edinburgh Geographical Society, undated (Folder 2: 2)
    - Map of Royal Yugoslavia, photocopy, undated (Folder 2: 2)
  - Memorabilia, 1935-1940 (Folder 2)
    - Recipes, undated (Folder 2: 3)
    - Buttons, copperplate for printing business card, box key, rosary, undated (Folder 2: 4)
    - Monetary notes (Folder 2: 5)
      Includes twenty-three Italian lira, five notes dated 1935 XIII, eighteen notes dated 1938 XVII
    - Coins (Folder 2: 5)
      Includes Royal Yugoslavia dinars, 1935, 1938, Republic of France francs, 1947, British West Africa shillings, 1938, 1940
- Correspondence, 1918-1972 (Box 2)
  Consists of letters, cards, and enclosures, arranged in three groups: Chronological, Milorad D. Drachkovitch, and Srpska Pravoslavna Crkva
  - Chronological, 1918-1972, undated (Folder 2)
    - 1918-1919, 1924 (Folder 2: 6)
    - 1939-1940 (Folder 2: 7)
    - 1941-1955 (Folder 2: 8-22)
    - 1957-1958 (Folder 2: 23-24)
    - 1960-1961 (Folder 2: 25-26)
    - 1963 (Folder 2: 27)
    - 1966-1972 (Folder 2: 28-34)
    - Undated (Folder 2: 35)
  - Drašković, Milorad M., 1945-1971 (Folder 2: 36)
  - Srpska Pravoslavna Crkva, 1969-1971 (Folder 2: 37)
- Writings, circa 1940-1970 (Box 3-8)
  Composed of a memoir, fragments, drafts, and notes on topics related to Royal Yugoslav relations with Bulgaria and Germany, Yugoslav émigrés' reflections on political conditions in post-war Yugoslavia, and an English-Serbian dictionary.
  Arranged alphabetically in two groups: Drafts, articles, fragments, and notes, and English-Serbian dictionary
  - Drafts, article fragments, and notes, undated (Folder 3-4)
    - Book reviews, holograph and typescript, undated (Folder 3: 1)
    - "Bugarska uoči II Svetskog Rata," typescript, undated (Folder 3: 2)
    - "Bulgaria and the Present War," holograph and typescript, undated (Folder 3: 3)
    - "Iz Nedavne Prošlosti," memoir draft, typescript, notes, and holograph, undated (Folder 3: 4-13)
    - II O Revizionizmu," typescript, undated (Folder 4: 1)
    - "Zrnce," typescript, undated (Folder 4: 2)
    - "Yugoslavia and Albania," typescript, undated (Folder 4: 3)
  - English-Serbian dictionary, undated (Folder 4-8)
    - Words, undated (Folder 4)
      - B, I, J, K, M (Folder 4: 4-15)
      - N, O, Q, U, V, X-Z (Folder 5: 1-12)
    - English-Serbian dictionary introduction, holograph, undated (Folder 5: 13)
    - Notes for dictionary A-Z holograph, undated (Folder 5: 14-15)
    - Notes for dictionary holograph, undated (Folder 6)
      - A-F (Folder 6: 1-11)
      - H-J, L-N, P-Ra (Folder 7: 1-10)
      - Rb-T, W, Y (Folder 8: 1-6)
    - Serbian words holograph, undated (Folder 8: 7)
    - Comments and notes holograph, undated (Folder 8: 8)
- Speeches and writings by others, circa 1940-1970 (Box 8-9)
  Contains fragments, drafts, notes and speeches by Milorad M. Drachkovitch and others.
  Arranged in three groups by form and author
  - Milorad M. Drachkovitch (Drašković) writings, 1952-1961 (Folder 8)
    - De Karl Marx à Léon Blum, Libraire E. Droz, Geneva, 1954 (Folder 8: 9)
    - "Les Crises du Socialisme Occidental," Bruges, 1958 (Folder 8: 10)
    - Lettre ouverte: A MM. Paul-Henri SPAAK et Max BUSET, open letter, Bruges, 15 December 1952 (Folder 8: 11)
    - "Rapport sur le 'Communisme National,'" typescript, undated (Folder 8: 12)
    - La Société Occidentale, Laboratoire des Changements Sociaux, booklet, 1961 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Writings by others, 1937-1967 (Folder 9)
    - Ciano, Galeazzo, Diary 1937-1943, translation (Folder 9: 1)
    - Doychinovich, Milan, Amanet,, booklet, 1969 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Drašković, Slobodan M., "Poštovani gospodine Predsedniče," typescript, Paris, 1947 March (Folder 9: 3)
    - Jefremović, Draģ B., "Rodoslovlje Ikonije iz Cerovca," typescript, circa 1962 (Folder 9: 4)
    - Miloyevitch (Milojević), Milan, G., 1942-1944 (Folder 9: 5-6)
      - "From the Realm of Our State Problems-In the Service of Yugoslavia," transcript, London, booklet, 1942 (Folder 9: 5)
      - Anglo-Yugoslav Cultural Relations, St. Clements Press, Ltd., London, 1944 (Folder 9: 6)
    - Pavlowitch, K. St., La Yougoslavie et l'Italie entre les deux guerres, les conversations Marinkovitch-Grandi (1930-1931), reprint, 1967 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Pipinelis, P., undated (Folder 9)
      - "La Question d'une Macédonie Autonome," typescript (Folder 9: 8)
      - "La Question de la Thrace," typescript (Folder 9: 9)
    - Ristić, Borislav M., 1944-1945 (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Zdrava Državna Osonva: Istina i Jedna linija-Jedan Put - Pravi Put za Sve," Današnj rat, No. 2, London, December 1944 (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Naša spoljno-politička situaciaj," Današnj rat, No. 3, London, December 1944 (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Igra sa psihologijom sa narodom ili sa sobom," Današnj rat, No. 4, London, January 1945 (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Izvor rata, današnji stadijum i perspective," Današnj rat, No. 5, London, January 1945 (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Naše teške prilike: Koordinacija i suprotnosti, ideje i stvarnosti," Današnj rat, No. 6, London, January 1945 (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Savremeni posljednji Cilj Života, Najteži Problem," Današnj rat, No. 7, London, January 1945 (Folder 9: 10)
      - "Naši kritični dani u Londonu," Današnj rat, No. 8, London, February 1945 (Folder 9: 10)
    - Smodlaka, Josip, "The Yugoslav-Italian Frontier Question," New Yugoslavia reprint, Nos. 7-10, June-July issue, undated (Folder 9: 11)
    - Unidentified authors, 1958, undated (Folder 9)
      - "Gospodin Djoka Pavlovic," typescript, undated (Folder 9: 12)
      - "Iz oblasti nasih državnih problema, U službi Jugoslavije," typescript, undated (Folder 9: 13)
      - "Pad Generala Simovića," Savremenik, typescript, April-May 1958 (Folder 9: 14)
      - "Pogron Srba (1941-1942), u Bosni i Hercegovini, u Svetlosti Istorije," typescript, undated (Folder 9: 15)
    - Miscellany, 1942 and undated (Folder 9: 16)
  - Speeches, 1942, undated (Folder 9)
    - General, unsigned, undated (Folder 9: 17)
    - "Commemoration of the Victims of Kragujevac," 1942. Includes speeches by Miloš Trifunovic, the Secretary for Education; the R.A. Butler, British Minster of Education; Hoste, Deputy Minster for Education, Belgium; Dimitrakakatisa, Greek Minister for Justice; Slvik Bolkesteina, G. Stronjski, Polish Minister of Information; and message from Queen Maria of Yugoslavia (Folder 9: 18)
- Royal Yugoslav government office file, 1935-1946 (Box 9-11)
  Contains correspondence, government documents and reports, financial records, and press releases related to Yugoslav-Bulgarian diplomatic relations and Yugoslav foreign policy, and Yugoslav émigré affairs in Great Britain. See also oversize materials
  Arranged chronologically by embassy posting
  - 1935 assignment to the Bucharest (Romania) embassy files (Folder 9)
    - New Ambassador, transfer documents, 1935 (Folder 9: 19)
  - 1940-1941 assignment to the Bern (Switzerland) embassy files (Folder 9)
    - New Ambassador, transfer documents, February 1940 (Folder 9: 20)
    - Bulgarian foreign affairs, comments, 1941 (Folder 9: 21)
  - 1940-1941 assignment to the Sofia (Bulgaria) embassy files (Folder 10)
    See also oversize materials
    - Office documents, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1941 (Folder 10: 1)
      - Speech upon becoming ambassador, transcript, undated (Folder 10: 2)
      - Cotton transfer arrangement from Varna, Bulgaria, to Odessa, Russia, 1941 (Folder 10: 3)
      - Financial statement, 11 April 1941 (Folder 10: 4)
      - Minutes of the committee on confidential documents and the book of codes, 1941 (Folder 10: 5)
    - Reports, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
      - Yugoslav Bulgarian political affairs, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
        - Russian role in Serbian-Bulgarian negotiation on September 1911, by Boris Nikolajev, 1940 (Folder 10: 6)
        - Yugoslav-Bulgarian long term collaboration, 1940 (Folder 10: 7)
        - Yugoslav-Bulgarian political affairs, ambassador's reports, 1940 (Folder 10: 8)
        - Yugoslav-Bulgarian treaty, 1940 (Folder 10: 9)
        - Yugoslav-Bulgarian relations, 1941 (Folder 10: 10)
      - Bulgarian political affairs, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
        - Bulgarian National Assembly on foreign political affairs, 1940 (Folder 10: 11)
        - Bulgarian officials on foreign affairs, 1940 (Folder 10: 12)
        - Bulgarian National Assembly on internal political affairs, 1940 (Folder 10: 13)
        - Bulgarian new approach towards the Balkan region, 1940 (Folder 10: 14)
        - Filov's government on Bulgarian foreign policy, circa 1940 (Folder 10: 15)
        - King Boris's speech on Bulgarian political affairs, report, 1940 (Folder 10: 16)
        - King Boris and Bulgarian-Yugoslav relations, comments by Bojan Smilov, 1940 (Folder 10: 17)
        - Makedonsko Pitanje, reports, 1940 (Folder 10: 18-20)
        - "The Macedonian Question," by Djoko Slijepčević, undated, 1940 (Folder 10: 21)
        - Rendell on the latest developments in Bulgaria, 23 December 1940 (Folder 10: 22)
        - Sofia University professors political association and activities in relation to Yugoslavia, report, 1940 (Folder 10: 23)
        - Bulgarian students' national committee members, list, 1941 (Folder 10: 24)
        - Bulgarian political affairs, 1941 (Folder 10: 25)
        - Bulgaria-Axis materials, 1941 (Folder 10: 26)
        - "Revizionistička kampanja," Bulgarian newspapers report, 1941 (Folder 10: 27)
      - Bulgarian relations with Germany and the Balkan region, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
        - German military in Bulgaria, 1941 (Folder 10: 28)
        - German political aspirations in the Balkan region, 1941 (Folder 10: 29)
        - Churchill on German's army in Bulgaria, 1941 (Folder 10: 30)
        - Bulgarian-Romanian treaty, 1940 (Folder 10: 31)
        - Bulgarian-Soviet political relations, 1941 (Folder 10: 32)
        - Council of Balkan treaty meeting, Belgrade, 1940 (Folder 10: 33)
        - Turkish-Bulgarian political affairs, 1940 (Folder 10: 34)
        - Vesti iz inostranstva, January-July 1940; January-March 1941 (Folder 10: 35-37)
  - 1941-1947 assignment to the Yugoslav government-in-exile ministry of foreign affairs, London files, 1934-1947 (Folder 10-11)
    - Office file, 1941-1947 (Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1941-1944 (Folder 10: 38)
      - Decree on Danilo Kalafatović's appointment as commander-in-chief of the Yugoslav army, April 1941 (Folder 10: 39)
      - "Aide-Mémoire on Bulgaria: The Bulgars in the Balkans,", March 1943 (Folder 10: 40)
      - Decree of the Ministry of War no. 1652, December 1944 (Folder 10: 41)
      - "Akt o Primirju,", August 1944 (Folder 10: 42)
      - "Request for Extradition of Yugoslav Nationals by Tito's Government," typescript report, 1946, by Slobodan Jovanović, the former president of the Government of Yugoslav National Union (Folder 10: 43)
      - Yugoslav Welfare Committee in Great Britain report, 1945-1947 (Folder 10: 44)
    - German policy documents, 1934; 1940,; 1946 (Folder 10)
      - Reports on German foreign policy, 1934; 1940 (Folder 10: 45)
      - "Minutes of a Meeting Called by Hitler in Berlin on 27 March 1941," typescript, May 1946, reproduced document based on the Oberkommando der Wehrmacht (OKW) of Germany files Enemy Documents section (Folder 10: 46)
    - Allied collaboration reports, 1942-1944 (Folder 10-11)
      - "Comité Interallié pour l'étude de l'armistice," London, 1942-1943, signed by Belgium, Czechoslovakia, France, Greece, Luxemburg, Norway, Netherlands, Poland, and Yugoslavia (Folder 10: 47)
      - "Brief Report on United Nations Commission on the Investigation of War Crimes," typescript, July 1944; and correspondence from Herbert Pell, September 1944 (Folder 11: 1)
  - 1943-1945 assignment to the Luxemburg and Belgian embassy (Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Folder 11: 2)
    - Report on Belgium and Anglo-American agreement on civilian administration of Belgium during the liberation and after, June 1944 (Folder 11: 3)
- Photographs, 1918-1965 (Box 11)
  Black and white prints of official and social engagements, family members, and children.
  Arranged by subject
  - Milanović with unidentified men, 1918; 1925,; 1941,; and undated (21 prints) (Folder 11: 4)
  - Portraits and identification prints, undated (22 prints) (Folder 11: 5)
  - Official gatherings, 1925; circa 1935,; 1943,; and undated (35 prints) (Folder 11: 6)
  - Social gathering depicting Vladimir J. Milanović with unidentified group of individuals at social events, undated (8 prints) (Folder 11: 7)
  - Family members and children's portraits, 1936-1969 (18 prints) (Folder 11: 8)
  - Miscellany (Folder 11: 9)
    - 'Kraljičina lađa,', 1922 (1 print) (Folder 11: 9)
    - Religious motif print, undated (1 print) (Folder 11: 9)
    - Unidentified ladies, undated (23 prints) (Folder 11: 9)
    - Unidentified individuals, undated (10 prints) (Folder 11: 9)
- Printed matter, 1933-1972 (Box 11-12)
  Contains newspapers, press releases, periodicals, clippings, and other material related to Yugoslav politics and developments in Yugoslavia and Europe during and after World War II.
  Arranged chronologically by name of publication
  - Gazeta Sprturilor, 1933 (Folder 11: 10)
  - Uput o Kraljevskim odlikovanjima, njihovom rangu inošenju, Belgrade, Serbia, 1939 (Folder 11: 11)
  - Booklets and brochures, 1940; 1947,; 1953,; 1969,; 1988 (Folder 11: 12)
  - Službene Novine Kraljevine Jugosavije, June, August 1942 (Folder 11: 13)
  - Direkcija za Informativnu Službu, September 1942; February 1943 (Folder 11: 14)
  - New Russian Vocabulary with Pronunciation, George G. Harrap & Co. Ltd, London, 1943 (Folder 11: 15)
  - Proceedings of the International Law Conference, London, 1944 (Folder 11: 16)
  - The Daily Telegraph, April 1946 (Folder 11: 17)
  - Politika, July 1946 (Folder 11: 18)
  - Glas Jugosavije, June 1947 (Folder 11: 19)
  - Congressional Record, 1951; 1953 (Folder 11: 20)
  - Seljačka Jugoslavija, 1952 (Folder 11: 21)
  - Reader's Digest, 1952-1953; 1964 (Folder 11: 22)
  - Naša Stvarnost, 1952-1955; 1957 (Folder 12: 1-3)
  - Naša Stvarnost, 1960 and undated (Folder 12: 4-5)
  - Poruka, November 1954 (Folder 12: 6)
  - Klic Triglava, June 1960 (Folder 12: 7)
  - Glas Kanadskih Srba, February 1960 (Folder 12: 8)
  - "Who Pulled the Trigger? Soviet Historians and the Origins of World War II," Notes and Views, circa 1960 (Folder 12: 9)
  - Beli Orao, May/June 1961 (Folder 12: 10)
  - Orbis, winter 1962 (Folder 12: 11)
  - National Review, 1962 (Folder 12: 12)
  - Iskra, May 1965 (Folder 12: 13)
  - Sloboda, December 1967 (Folder 12: 14)
  - Jugoslavija, August-September 1947 (Folder 12: 15)
  - The Serbian Review, June 1968 (Folder 12: 16)
  - The Serbian National Committee Information Bulletin, 1968 (Folder 12: 17)
  - Glas Ravne Gore, 1968; 1972 (Folder 12: 18)
  - Parohiski Vesnik, December 1969 (Folder 12: 19)
  - "Draža Mihailović club," flyers, 1969 (Folder 12: 20)
  - Glas Srpske Opštine, London, December 1969; April 1971,; March 1972 (Folder 12: 21)
  - "Events in Hungary, Chronology 1933-1944,", undated (Folder 12: 22)
  - Clippings in Serbo-Croatian, French, and English, 1941-1971 (Folder 12: 23-25)
  - Clippings in English, 1941-1971; 1948-1968; and undated (Folder 12: 26-27)
- Oversize materials, 1968-1941 (Box 13)
  Consists of certificates, land registry record, and government documents.
  Arranged by physical form in two groups
  - Svjedočanstvo, holograph, 1868, a land-registry record that includes additions to the document from 1928, 1934 (Folder 13: 1-2)
  - School and degree records, 1906-1922 (Folder 13: 1-2)
  - Acceptance certificate of Vladimir J. Milanović as a Royal Yugoslav embassy second secretary in Rome by the Italian government, April 1924 (Folder 13: 1-2)
  - Decree on the appointment and salary grades, 1926; 1927,; 1928 (Folder 13: 1-2)